<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Rishi's Blog - rishikc.com]]></title><description><![CDATA[I write code that runs on your browsers, phones, and desktops. Experienced in building websites, mobile applications, DevSecOps tools, and more. ]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 04:24:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[The Ultimate SEO checklist for your website]]></title><description><![CDATA[As a developer, you can improve your page rank with a few simple and easy to follow tips. This ultimate SEO series includes different ways to improve web ranking from basics to fairly advanced technical aspects.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/ultimate-web-developer-seo-check-list/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/ultimate-web-developer-seo-check-list/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>This article is the first installment of an ongoing series of articles I’m writing on search engine optimization from a developer’s viewpoint. The series is meant to be a quick, bite-sized bundle of information that developers can immediately apply to their websites without any previous SEO experience. For this piece, we’ll start with…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Will Artificial Intelligence fully replace Web Developers?]]></title><description><![CDATA[In today's digital age, businesses increasingly use AI-powered solutions to boost efficiency and cut costs. However, when it comes to web development, there is no substitute for human expertise.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/will-artificial-intelligence-replace-web-developers/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/will-artificial-intelligence-replace-web-developers/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>As the research and development of artificial intelligence keep picking up pace every day, businesses have started considering or already incorporated AI-powered solutions to boost efficiency and cut costs. In recent days, we have seen people talk about how AI might replace a massive chunk of the workforce or take over processes that used…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Grays and Whites]]></title><description><![CDATA[Sometimes we try to define something and figure out we don't need to. Or we slap the closest label on it and move on. We don't want to bother ourselves too much with the grays because the grays demand energy. Nevertheless, some situations need that we describe certain things.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/grays-and-whites/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/grays-and-whites/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Sometimes we try to define something and figure out we don’t need to. Or we slap the closest label on it and move on. We don’t want to bother ourselves too much with the grays because the grays demand energy. Nevertheless, some situations need that we describe certain things. Sentiments

I’m yet to fully understand the concept of a job in…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trains and the Buddhist principle of impermanence]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Buddhist principle of impermanence, where everything in life is constantly changing, and nothing is permanent. Even something as grand and impressive as a train is also subject to this. Despite this, trains are crucial in connecting people and places, providing transportation essential to our society.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/trains-and-buddhist-principle-of-impermanence/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/trains-and-buddhist-principle-of-impermanence/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Imagine you are traveling on a train through the rural parts of India. Apart from the fields and beautiful views for the most part, the following two common sights are that of shacks and railway crossings. As we pass an intersection, I either mindlessly stare outside or look at everything around me, including the faces we are passing by…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Automate lighthouse audits for your Progressive Web App]]></title><description><![CDATA[Automate your lighthouse audits with Mocha and chai instead of manually performing the audits on your progressive web application every time. Run all the tests programmatically in your continuous integration/deployment environments or on your local system.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/automate-lighthouse-audits-progressive-web-app/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/automate-lighthouse-audits-progressive-web-app/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>We all know how valuable and helpful the insights are from lighthouse audits when we’re developing our web applications. But the way most of us check is manually through Chrome dev tools or the lighthouse extension, which in my opinion, is not very productive. For those of us who don’t know, there are mainly four ways of auditing our web…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Managing React application state - without using Redux!]]></title><description><![CDATA[In this article, we are going to explore a new way of managing React application state by using hooks. We'll try to leverage the React.useContext and React.useReducer hooks to manage our application state without using redux.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/managing-react-application-state-without-redux/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/managing-react-application-state-without-redux/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Disclaimer: This solution is best suited for small scale projects, and its main motive is to explore the new APIs React provides rather than trying to replace any traditional solutions. So when was the last time you tried managing application state, without Redux? As far as I can remember, for me, it was probably during the time I had…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Architecting React Applications - Part II]]></title><description><![CDATA[Like any other web application, React applications also require close attention to their architecture. Introduction of Hooks might have shown us new ways of abstractions in our React applications, but what about so many applications that are still using older versions of React?]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/architecting-react-applications-redux-store-services-and-sagas/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/architecting-react-applications-redux-store-services-and-sagas/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>This article is a continuation of my previous article - Architecting React Applications - where I wrote about a simple way to architect almost any React application into a modular structure. In this article, I am going to write about a relatively complex codebase with things such as application state management. We’ll build upon the same…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Architecting React Applications]]></title><description><![CDATA[Like any other web application, React applications also require close attention to their architecture. Introduction of Hooks might have shown us new ways of abstractions in our React applications but what about so many applications that are still using older versions of React?]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/architecting-react-applications/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/architecting-react-applications/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>React has always been popular for its short learning curve and easy to use APIs. But if you have been working with this popular javascript library for a while now, you might agree with me on this one as well – If you don’t pay attention to it’s structure it will soon become an unmaintainable mess. Before joining my first job, I had some…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Android Emulator for React Native in Mac, Linux and Windows]]></title><description><![CDATA[Let's quickly install Android emulator in Mac, Linux and Windows - all from command line. We'll do a minimal installation with android sdk, required tools and ofcourse - the emulator! Then we'll setup a virtual device and test run to check if it was properly installed and use it in a better way.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/native-app-emulator-android-mac-linux-ios-install-command-line/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/native-app-emulator-android-mac-linux-ios-install-command-line/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>So let me ask you first — How many of you have installed Android Studio only to use the emulator for your native app? Oh, and don’t forget the way your system struggles when you try to run it!

And no, I’m not just talking about any average system — even my Macbook Pro with 8GB of RAM makes a lot of noise!

A lot of you might have also…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Persist and Encrypt data in React Native applications]]></title><description><![CDATA[Learn how to store data on a mobile device securely. Set up persistent storage for your app using redux-persist and encrypt it with redux-persist-transform-encrypt.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/encrypt-persisted-data-react-native-mobile-application/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/encrypt-persisted-data-react-native-mobile-application/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>Users’ need for privacy and data security keeps increasing daily and it will always be in demand. So how do we store data on a mobile device without worrying about security? In this article, we’ll go through an effortless and quick way to: Set up persistent storage for our app and store any user data locally.

Encrypt the data to make…</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shrink your React Native application size dramatically!]]></title><description><![CDATA[To reduce your react native application size for android, we'll need to configure the build file to generate a compressed bundle for your react native app and then split it into multiple bundles for all architectures so that it can be made more lightweight.]]></description><link>https://rishikc.com/articles/shrink-react-native-application-build-size-android/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://rishikc.com/articles/shrink-react-native-application-build-size-android/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>So you made a cool and awesome looking React Native app, and now you’re ready to build it and maybe publish it to the store — But worried about it if the users would want to install it given its build size? Or maybe you just want to keep it lightweight and not take too much memory unnecessarily when it can be packed into a smaller size?

O…</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>